<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
  <!-- generated by https://github.com/cabo/kramdown-rfc2629 version 1.0.28 -->

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4790 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4790.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5234 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5234.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6265 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6265.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7231 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7231.xml">
]>

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-west-cookie-priority" category="std" updates="6265">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="cookie-priority">A Retention Priority Attribute for HTTP Cookies</title>

    <author initials="S." surname="Huang" fullname="Samuel Huang">
      <organization>Google</organization>
      <address>
        <email>huangs@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="M." surname="West" fullname="Mike West">
      <organization>Google, Inc</organization>
      <address>
        <email>mkwst@google.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2016"/>

    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>HTTPbis</workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>


<t>This document defines the <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx> attribute for HTTP cookies.  This
attribute allows servers to specify a retention priority for HTTP
cookies that will be respected by user agents during cookie eviction.</t>



    </abstract>


  </front>

  <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>This document defines the <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx> attribute for HTTP cookies. Using
the <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx> attribute, servers may indicate that certain cookies
should be protected, and others preferentially deleted. When a user
agent evicts cookies in the enforcement of a per-domain quota, lower
priority cookies will be deleted first, potentially preserving
higher-priority cookies that would otherwise have been deleted
according to the rules of <xref target="RFC6265"></xref>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="terminology-and-notation" title="Terminology and notation">

<t>The key words “MUST”, “MUST NOT”, “REQUIRED”, “SHALL”, “SHALL NOT”, “SHOULD”,
“SHOULD NOT”, “RECOMMENDED”, “MAY”, and “OPTIONAL” in this document are to be
interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.</t>

<t>This specification uses the Augmented Backus-Naur Form (ABNF) notation of
<xref target="RFC5234"/>.</t>

<t>Two sequences of octets are said to case-insensitively match each other if and
only if they are equivalent under the <spanx style="verb">i;ascii-casemap</spanx> collation defined in
<xref target="RFC4790"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="overview" title="Overview">

<t>This section outlines a way for an origin server to indicate the
retention priority for individual cookies and for the user agent to
respect retention priorities during cookie eviction.</t>

<t>To indicate a cookie’s retention priority, the origin server includes
a <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx> attribute in the <spanx style="verb">Set-Cookie</spanx> HTTP response header. A value
of “Low” indicates that the cookie should be given lower retention
priority (evicted prior to other cookies). A value of “High” indicates
that a cookie should be given higher retention priority (evicted
after other cookies). The value of “Medium” corresponds to the default
behavior.</t>

<t>In order to prevent starvation of functionality dependent on low- and
medium-priority cookies, a fraction of the cookie quota should be
reserved for them.</t>

<t><xref target="RFC6265"/>, Section 5.3, describes a strategy that user agents must
follow when “removing excess cookies”. A user agent implementing the
current specification for a retention priority attribute will
implement an extended priority order, dividing the second priority
(“Cookies that share a domain field with more than a predetermined
number of other cookies”) into multiple levels corresponding to the
three retention priorities.</t>

<t>As a result, when the cookies for a given domain exceed user agent
limits, cookies with low priority will be evicted first, followed by
medium and high priority cookies.</t>

<section anchor="examples" title="Examples">

<t>Using the Priority attribute, an origin server may assign a retention
priority to a cookie stored by a user agent. For example, the origin
server may prioritize the retention of session security tokens while
indicating that superficial data such as a user’s favorite color
should be discarded in preference to other data.</t>

<t>The following figure illustrates a series of 33 cookies received by a
user-agent from the example.com server during one or more HTTP
responses.  Each cookie is represented by an L, M, or H indicating
low, medium, or high priority, respectively.</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
== Least Recently Accessed -> Most Recently Accessed ==

   M L H H H H M H L L M M M M M M M L L L L L M M M M M H M M L L M
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Assume that the user agent is configured to evict all but 25 cookies
from a domain when the number of cookies exceeds 31. <xref target="RFC6265"/>
specifies the following eviction order. Cookies are separated in the
vertical axis by priority.  Evicted cookies are labeled with a ‘1’
and retained cookies with an ‘X’.</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
== Least Recently Accessed -> Most Recently Accessed ==

L    1             X X               X X X X X                 X X
M  1           1       X X X X X X X           X X X X X   X X     X
H      1 1 1 1   1                                       X
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>A user agent that implements the current specification, reserving
room for 5 low-, 15 medium-, and 5 high-priority cookies, would
implement a modified eviction order as follows. ‘1’, ‘2’, and ‘3’
indicate cookies evicted during various phases of the algorithm.</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
== Least Recently Accessed -> Most Recently Accessed ==

L    1             1 1               1 1 X X X                 X X
M  2           2       X X X X X X X           X X X X X   X X     X
H      3 X X X   X                                       X
]]></artwork></figure>

<t>Of note is that the retention priority does not impact the relative
eviction priority of cookies being evicted due to the global
threshold (i.e., once no domain exceeds the per-domain threshold).
Furthermore, this new attribute has no effect on domains that do not
send it.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="server-requirements" title="Server Requirements">

<t>This section describes the syntax and semantics of the <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx>
cookie attribute.</t>

<section anchor="syntax" title="Syntax">

<t>The Set-Cookie HTTP response header syntax is defined in <xref target="RFC6265"/>,
Section 4.1.1.  The grammar defined therein provides for tokens of
type ‘extension-av’.  The Priority attribute is a subset of
‘extension-av’ that may appear zero or one times in a given ‘set-
cookie-header’.  If it appears, the ‘priority’ attribute must conform
to the following grammar:</t>

<figure><artwork><![CDATA[
priority-av    = "Priority=" priority-value
priority-value = "Low" / "Medium" / "High"
]]></artwork></figure>

</section>
<section anchor="semantics-non-normative" title="Semantics (Non-Normative)">

<t>This section describes a simplified semantics of the <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx>
attribute in the <spanx style="verb">Set-Cookie</spanx> HTTP response header. The full semantics
are described in Section 5.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="the-priority-attribute" title="The ‘Priority’ Attribute">

<t>The <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx> attribute indicates a retention priority relative to
other cookies from the same domain as the cookie carrying the
attribute. During cookie eviction in enforcement of per-domain
cookie limits, <spanx style="verb">Low</spanx> priority cookies will be evicted before <spanx style="verb">Medium</spanx> and
<spanx style="verb">Medium</spanx> before <spanx style="verb">High</spanx>. Cookies without a specified priority are
considered to have <spanx style="verb">Medium</spanx> priority.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="user-agent-requirements" title="User Agent Requirements">

<t><xref target="RFC6265"/>, Section 5.2 describes how user agents must parse the value
of the <spanx style="verb">Set-Cookie</spanx> HTTP response header. This specification provides
additional processing steps that user agents must follow when they
encounter a <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx> attribute.</t>

<t><spanx style="verb">Set-Cookie</spanx> headers that do not specify the <spanx style="verb">Priority</spanx> attribute MUST be
treated as if the attribute was present and had the value Medium.</t>

<section anchor="the-priority-attribute-1" title="The ‘Priority’ Attribute">

<t>If the <spanx style="verb">attribute-name</spanx> case-insensitively matches the string
“Priority”, the user agent MUST process the <spanx style="verb">cookie-av</spanx> as follows:</t>

<t>If the <spanx style="verb">attribute-value</spanx> case-insensitively matches the string “Low”,
the cookie is assigned a low retention priority.</t>

<t>If the <spanx style="verb">attribute-value</spanx> case-insensitively matches the string
“Medium”, the cookie is assigned a medium retention priority.</t>

<t>If the <spanx style="verb">attribute-value</spanx> case-insensitively matches the string “High”,
the cookie is assigned a high retention priority.</t>

<t>Otherwise, the cookie is assigned a medium retention priority.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="storage-model" title="Storage Model">

<t><xref target="RFC6265"/>, Section 6.1 recommends that user agents set limits on the
number of cookies they will store. <xref target="RFC6265"/>, Section 5.3, describes
a strategy that user must follow when “removing excess cookies”.</t>

<t>A user agent implementing the current specification for a retention
priority attribute will set aside a small portion of its storage
quota for low-priority cookies, and another portion for medium-
priority cookies. During eviction, compatible user agents will
implement an extended priority order, dividing the second priority
(“Cookies that share a domain field with more than a predetermined
number of other cookies”) into three, according to the retention
priorities and the space reserved for them. Assuming that no other
extensions ammend the rules defined in <xref target="RFC6265"/>, a compatible user
agent MUST therefore evict cookies in the following priority order (L
and M refer to the amount of space reserved for low- and medium-
priority cookies respectively, per domain).  As per <xref target="RFC6265"/>, within
each category the least-recently accessed cookies should be deleted
first.</t>

<t><list style="numbers">
  <t>Expired cookies.</t>
  <t>Cookies with a low retention priority that share a domain field
with more than a predetermined number of other cookies, excluding
the first L low-priority cookies from that domain.</t>
  <t>Cookies with a low or medium retention priority that share a
domain field with more than a predetermined number of other
cookies, excluding the first L + M low- and medium-priority
cookies from that domain.</t>
  <t>Cookies that share a domain field with more than a predetermined
number of other cookies.</t>
  <t>All cookies.</t>
</list></t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="implementation-considerations" title="Implementation Considerations">

<t>This specification extends <xref target="RFC6265"/> in order to enable improved
behaviour when servers are unable or unwilling to keep the number of
distinct cookies served by their domains within the limits of user
agents. As this specification is unlikely to ever achieve universal
adoption by user agents, servers SHOULD gracefully degrade if their
specifed cookie retention priorities are not respected.</t>

</section>


  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title='Normative References'>

&RFC2119;
&RFC4790;
&RFC5234;
&RFC6265;
&RFC7231;


    </references>

    <references title='Informative References'>

<reference anchor="Wright2013" target="https://docs.google.com/a/google.com/file/d/0B3o1IlTKoADVRllKWGlyWGxIVTg/edit">
  <front>
    <title>A Retention Priority Attribute for HTTP Cookies</title>
    <author initials="E." surname="Wright" fullname="Erik Wright">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <author initials="S." surname="Huang" fullname="Samuel Huang">
      <organization></organization>
    </author>
    <date year="n.d."/>
  </front>
</reference>


    </references>


<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>This document is based heavily on an earlier draft written by Erik Wright and
Samuel Huang <xref target="Wright2013"/>, and the experimentation done in cooperation with
Google’s login team.</t>

</section>


  </back>
</rfc>

